A Guide to the Wetsel Seed Company Oral Histories, 1911-1990: SdArch 1
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Wetsel Seed Company Oral Histories
1911-1990
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Rennyson, David James
Wetsel, Nelson T.
Thomas, Maxine
SdArch 1
216
.51 cubic feet; 3 folders, 4 audiocassettes, 7 cds
The Wetsel Seed Company Oral Histories, 1970-1990, is comprised of interview transcripts, audio recordings, a pamphlet, and background papers, documenting the history of the Wetsel Seed Company, of Harrisonburg, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated on April 23, 1990 by David James Rennyson.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically.
Bio/Historical Note
Wetsel Seed Company was founded in 1911 by Daniel M. Wetsel and his eldest son, Arnold W. Wetsel in Harrisonburg, Virginia. It was originally called D.M. Wetsel and Son, and was the Shenandoah Valley's first seed, feed and plant business. In 1915 it changed names to become Wetsel Seed Company, Inc. Daniel Wetsel was known to experiment and develop various seed products, notably those associated with corn and tomatoes. The business eventually developed mail order catalogs and truck delivery services, opened up additional stores in Waynesboro and developed a garden center. Wetsel Seed Company has involved four generations of family members, including Earl H., Robert E., Nelson T., and Thomas M. Wetsel. The company was purchased by BFG Supply Company in 2011.
Scope and Content
The Wetsel Seed Company Oral Histories, 1970-1990, is comprised of interview transcripts, audio recordings, a pamphlet, and background papers, documenting the history of the Wetsel Seed Company, Inc. of Harrisonburg, Virginia, from its beginnings as the Shenandoah Valley's first seed/feed/plant business in 1911 to its status as a multi-state seed/plant/lawn-garden firm in 1971. It includes an interview with Nelson T. Wetsel, former president and consultant for the Wetsel Seed Company; an interview with Maxine Thomas, former employee (mostly in payroll accounting) at the Wetsel Seed Company in Harrisonburg, Va; a pamphlet, written by Russell Stultz, which gives a history of Wetsel Seed Company, Inc., from 1911 to 1971; and background papers written by interviewer, and JMU history undergraduate student, David James Rennyson.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Agricultural industries -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Farm supply industries -- Virginia -- Rockingham County; Garden centers (Retail trade); Seed industry and trade -- History; Seed industry and trade -- Equipment and supplies; Seed industry and trade -- Personnel management; Distributors (Seed industry and trade); Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Rockingham County (Va.) -- Industries -- Sources; Family-owned business enterprises -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Wetsel Seed Co.
Genre and Form Terms:
oral histories (literary works)
- 1-1: House of Wetsel Seeds 1911-1971 Pamphlet, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Records the growth and development of the Wetsel Seed Company, Inc. of Rockingham County, Va., from its beginnings as the Shenandoah Valley's first seed/feed/plant business in 1911 to its status as a multi-state seed/plant/lawn-garden firm in 1971. Gives biographical information about the founder, Daniel M. Wetsel, who experimented and developed various seed products, notably those associated with corn (and also tomato). Mentions his contributions, beginning in 1896, with the marketing of seeds and plants produced by the "Green Island Seed Farm at Port Republic, Va., with expansion/distribution to Harrisonburg and surrounding areas (cont.) Records important dates and changes in the development of the business (ex. in 1911, known as D.M. Wetsel & Son, with a store located in Harrisonburg; in 1915, it became known as the Wetsel Seed Company, Inc., with the eldest son, Arnold W., as co-founder). Refers to contributions made during World War I (victory gardens); 1929 depression, drought of 1930; exports (ex. grass seeds) during and following World War II, to various states and countries. Mentions development of mail order catalogs, delivery schedule calendars; seed cleaning/processing/packaging/storing service; truck delivery service; Waynesboro, Va. branch store; and development of the garden center. Mentions acquisitions of various buildings, etc. Relates contributions of four generations of family members, besides D. M. and A. W., including Earl H., Robert E., Nelson T., and Thomas M. Wetsel.
- 1-2: Nelson T. Wetsel interviewed by David James Rennyson, January 24, 1990
  Records the reminisces and viewpoints of Nelson Wetsel, former president, now consultant for the Wetsel Seed Company, recently bought out by Southern States. Includes a brief history of the company, which began as a family-owned business in 1911 and now employs close to 200 workers. Discusses the development/diversification of the firm over the years from primarily a local (Shenandoah Valley) seed business to a multi-state, etc. wholesale distributor of lawn and garden supplies, and supplier for the professional grower (greenhouses, nurseries) and turf grass industry. Gives biographical information about various family members, their contributions, and the general sense of what it was like to be part of a family-owned business (the company's policies, philosophy, employees). Reflects on recent developments with the Southern States association; gives views on the future
  - Transcript, January 24, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (cont.) More specifically, discusses the following: diversity of products (including grass seeds such as varieties of bluegrass, orchard grass; lawn/indoor and outdoor garden/professional grower supplies such as fertilizers, pesticides, insecticides, herbicides, gardening tools, soils, containers; supplies specifically for greenhouses/nurseries, such as cuttings and rooted plugs; hydroseed turf industry). Describes various aspects/percentage of business trade and market: primarily wholesale/distributor; some middleman relations; retailer; associations with dealers and growers. Discusses Harrisonburg and Waynesboro stores; also warehouse branches
  - Original audiocassette #1, January 24, 1990 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA001-CS-001)
    Discusses various aspects of business management including: direct mail and other forms of advertisement (5 different types of catalogs, the Seed News, WESCO trade logo); development of a distribution system with delivery schedule calendars, truck delivery service and warehouses in various locations such as the Eastern shore; acquisition of numerous buildings; bookkeeping/accounting aspects, internal organization; employee/employer relations including hiring practices, women employees, salesmen; public relations with vendors/growers/agricultural colleges, trade fairs/shows; also community relations such as with James Madison University. Discusses changes in technology and its influence on the company, competitors, and outside influences of Southern States on organization structure, etc.
  - Original audiocassette #2, January 24, 1990 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA001-CS-002)
    Talks about the family philosophy of hard work, integrity, service; mentions numerous family members and their contributions, including: Daniel M., Arnold W., Earl H., Robert E., Thomas, and Jeff Wetsel. Also mentions Wampler family associations.
  - Original audiocassette #3, January 24, 1990 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA001-CS-003)
  - Preservation master cd #1 (Box 1, Cd SA001-OP-001)
  - Preservation master cd #2 (Box 1, Cd SA001-OP-002)
  - Preservation master cd #3 (Box 1, Cd SA001-OP-003)
- 1-3: Maxine Thomas interviewed by David James Rennyson, March 14, 1990
  Records the reminisces and viewpoints of Maxine Thomas, a forty-two year employee (mostly in payroll accounting) at the Wetsel Seed Company in Harrisonburg, Va. Describes experiences and standpoints from the perspective of a non-family member, women and long-time employee at Wetsel's. Gives brief descriptions of various aspects of her work; some recollections concerning employee-employer relations, the growth of the company over the years, and memories of family members (Arnold W., Earl, Nelson, Bob (Robert), Tom, and Jeff Wetsel). Mentions growth in number of employees from around ten in 1949 to close to 200 in 1990. Briefly describes technological changes, such as the advent of computers; hiring practices; fringe benefits, etc. Mentions the number of salesmen; truck drivers; a few long-standing employees. Names the various states which are a part of the company's delivery/distribution service area
  - Transcript, March 14, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original audiocassette, March 14, 1990 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA001-CS-004)
  - Preservation master cd (Box 1, Cd SA001-OP-004)